wa alaikum wa rahmatullahi wa barakatuh, wa alaikum wa salam wa rahmatullahi wa barakatuh,
Sallallahu alayhi wa alaihi wa sallam, Mubarakatuh.
Our book on these days is Al-Adab al-Mufrat.
And we are about, we are discussing issues,
expressions that are lawful for the Muslim to say,
and expressions that are not lawful.
Expressions that are lawful, but that some of the Muslims,
they think that they are not lawful.
For example, yesterday we discussed Khosu Khuzakh.
Khosu Khuzakh, referring to the rainbow.
I'm sure we remember the rainbow we see on the sky.
We discussed this yesterday.
Rainbows usually are a product of the twin process of reflection and refraction,
as we have come to understand from basic science.
Arabs refer to the rainbow as Khosu Khuzakh.
Some of the scholars have mentioned that referring to the rainbow as Khosu Khuzakh,
is not a lawful expression.
Some of the scholars say that referring to the rainbow as Khosu Khuzakh,
is not an expression that is lawful.
So, Imam al-Bukhari here in Al-Adab al-Mufrid,
he seeks to affirm that using the expression Khosu Khuzakh.
Khosu means the arc, something that is curved,
perhaps cuts an orange into two.
One part of it is Khosu, that shape, that's curvedly shaped,
at the top, like the diameter of a circle.
If you cut a circle from the middle, or from any part of it,
even just cut across one point, across the other,
like obtaining a radius or something.
If you obtain a radius, will you get an arc? No.
If you get a radius, will you get an arc? No.
But if you get a diameter, the upper or the lower part of that diameter
will give you an arc. That arc is the Khos.
That's why the bow is also the Khos.
So, Arabs would refer to the rainbow as Khosu Khuzakh,
the arc or the bow of Khosakh.
So, it remains, what do they understand to mean Khosakh?
We have a Hadith that has come from the Prophet, alayhi salatu was salam,
that La Ta Kulu Kousa Khosakh, don't say Khosu Khosakh,
because Khosakh, Shayqanul, that word Khosakh,
is the name of a devil or a demon amongst the jinns.
But the ulama have established that that Hadith is Hadith al-Mawduh.
Like we said in class yesterday, al-Imam al-Albani discussed it
in salat al-Ahadith al-Dha'ifa. The Hadith is not authentic.
To say that Khosakh refers to the name of a devil.
In fact, in ancient Arabs, Arab literature,
we also have it to say that Khosakh is the name of the idol
responsible for the rainbow itself, for the Khos itself.
All of these are narrations that are weak and unreliable.
But because of these two things, some of the scholars have ruled
that they don't say Khosu Khosakh, if Khosu Khosakh,
if Khosakh refers to the name of a devil, or Khosakh refers
to the name of an idol, they think it's responsible for the Khos.
There is no lawful to say that, because the Khos belongs to Allah.
So they say instead of saying Khosu Khosakh,
you should say what Khosullah, the act that belongs to Allah.
In fact, you can say Khosul Mator, the act of rain.
Why? It is usually formed, of course, from physics.
We understand that the rains come after, the rainbow come after,
within some rainfall, since it's a joint result of a process
of reflection and refraction.
So you can say Khosu Khosakh, the act that becomes formed after rains.
So, but a stronger linguistic and historic narration shows
that the Arabs started to refer to the rainbow, the rainbow
that we know as Khosu Khosakh, because the first times
they noticed it, it was noticed around a mountain at Muzdalifa,
called Jabal Khosakh.
So it's like saying that Khos we saw around Khosakh mountain.
That was one narrative about how it became to be called Khosu Khosakh.
Another report said that it became called Khosu Khosakh,
because Khosakh is from Taqzih, and Taqzih refers to At-tazyeen wa-tah-zeen.
At-tazyeen is beautification.
So the Khos, the act of the rainbow beautifies the sky.
So it's like saying the act or that curve that beautifies the sky.
We see that the various colors of the rainbow appears on the rainbow.
So from the aspects of beautification, it was called Khosakh.
And so it is lawful for us to say Khosu Khosakh.
The entire discuss is about understanding what should we say,
what should we should not say, what we can say, what we cannot say.
In class yesterday, we also discussed the truth saying that
Ya'lamu Allah or Allahu Ya'lamu Allah knows it,
regarding something you are not sure about,
or regarding something you don't even know about.
Don't say Allah knows it.
Something happens like we gave the example yesterday, one, two, three happened.
So they asked you what happened?
You said A, B, C, Allahu Ya'lamu, A, B, C happened.
Ah, it means what you are saying is that what Allah knows was,
regarding the matter A, B, C, you are ascribing A, B, C to Allah.
When in reality what happened was one, two, three,
meaning you are ascribing to Allah something different from what occurs in his knowledge.
Like telling a lie and ascribing that lie to Allah Subhanahu wa Ta'ala.
So that is not lawful.
If you know something, yes, you can say this expression that
Allahu Ya'lamu, if you know that is how it is,
you want to affirm that what you have said is correct,
and you know it to be correct.
Al-Imamun Nawawi said,
Falaa Ba'sa bi dhaliq.
There is no blame.
If you knew that the matter was one, two, three,
and you are affirming that it is one, two, three, not correct.
It is not inappropriate to say it is one, two, three.
But if you don't know, don't say Allahu Ya'lamu,
regarding something that you say, you have the answer to be wrong,
and yet you are making Allah a witness over something you know to be wrong.
Likewise, when you don't know, you are not certain about what exactly was the matter.
Don't make Allah a witness or ascribe the knowledge of,
to the knowledge of Allah, something you are not sure of.
In fact, for us itself, even without an ascription,
have we not been prohibited in the Qur'an, from saying what we don't know?
Don't say what you don't know about,
because Allah will ask you about what you say as Allah mentioned in Surah Al-Turk.
Don't say what you don't know about.
If you don't know, say, I don't know about it.
Similarly, when a learned person is asked a question of knowledge,
if he does not know, he should say, I don't know.
La adil, la adil.
But when you don't know, you say Allahu Ya'lamu.
Many of the scholars say, no, don't say that.
If you don't know, say la adil, la adil.
But if you know, after full explanations and all of these,
you cap it all up by saying Allahu Ya'lamu,
by way of humbling yourself, by way of affirming
that absolute knowledge of every matter,
comprehensive knowledge of every matter,
having and encompassing understanding of every matter belongs to Allah,
then that is correct.
So, you can see that our Deen Islam places a lot of emphasis on things we say.
And you say this, or you should not say this.
When yesterday, we referred to Sheikh Bakr ibn Abi Zaid,
who was saying and affirming that what al-Imam al-Bukhari did here,
by telling us that Babu Qawsu al-Quzah al-Babun Qawsu al-Quzah,
is to affirm that it is lawful to say Qawsu al-Quzah regarding the rainbow.
We referred to his book Mu'jumu al-Mana'i al-Lafziyah.
That book is a very big book, very big.
More than 500 pages, more than 600 pages.
And all that it was talking about, things that we can say, things that we cannot say.
It means there is a lot of emphasis in our religion regarding Hibzul-Islam,
watching what you say, being certain what you say.
Can I say this as a Muslim? Should I not say this as a Muslim?
From the things that we studied yesterday, it's about Al-Majarra.
Al-Majarra now, it's a technical word amongst the Arabs to refer to the Milky Way.
But in the earlier times, the early Muslims described Al-Majarra.
Yes, the word can be used, words in technical usage can be borrowed from linguistic usage.
It can be borrowed from linguistic understanding and employed for modern-day use technically.
Even in English language, that one occurs.
Look at that word. I usually make an example with it.
F-O-R-C-E, force.
In language, it means you cannot compel me to do something.
You cannot push me. You cannot push me in any way, whether physically or mentally.
Pushing the person and making him do it.
That is force against his will anyway.
So, but today it is employed in physics and in fact in chemistry.
The way it is even used in both science may be different slightly.
The way it may be used in both may be slightly different.
So you say force, you want to push something from the ground.
It is there originally. That thing has an original inertia.
It does not want to move.
You need a force that is above the weight of that object for that object to move.
So that is that you are compelling it to move against its will.
It will now move when your employed force is bigger than its own resistance.
As if to say you made him to move against his will.
But when the will not to move is lower than the force to move, then it will move.
So you can see this understanding was brought.
And then force, forcing somebody to do something, we began to ascribe units to it in science.
So the same thing Al Majarrah.
Majarrah refers to a huge calabash looking structure inside the sky.
Far away from which water poured from the skies, like a gateway to the sky.
It was far away. So they used to consider it as a gateway into the heavens.
But today Al Majarrah, most literal translators will refer to Al Majarrah as the Milky Way.
And we know what it means. The Milky Way is the world of gases far away.
World of gases far away from us. So far away.
So words can be used in one form at a particular generation and in another generation it is used in another form.
In all of that we want to know what is lawful for us to say as Muslims.
What is not lawful? What is discouraged? What is encouraged?
In fact, in some cases during Ibadat what is compulsory?
Like the recitation of Surat al-Fatiha when we are in Salah.
So this is just a recap of the entirety of our lesson for the past few weeks till we had the class yesterday.
As I speak I would like to obtain a permission to leave the class.
And by the will of Allah we can come back to class next week.
Or can we make it a QA session? Can we continue today in a QA session?
Or we come back to class in the next week because I am very mentally occupied.
Like we said we have a few questions. Can we take a few questions?
We can take a few questions and stop on the dot of the time. We can do that too.
The first question I can see here says, when we are praying during sujood,
do we have to say, when we pray during sujood, do we have to say and repeat
In every sujood, all the last Salawat during Atiyah and Tasha'ud suffice?
In Salat, what we have been told to do in sujood basically is to say,
In sujood, in Salat, the basic thing to say we must say,
When we are in sujood, we must say,
We can also say,
Saying it once is absolutely compulsory.
Saying these expressions at least once, the ulama say it is compulsory.
But to say it twice and thrice are very strongly encouraged.
So we are, as we explained.
Now if the individual wants to say,
Like the Prophet Sallallahu Alaihi Wasallam encouraged us to make a lot of dua in our sujood.
In fact he said,
It is most very likely that you will be granted your request.
You now want to make dua in your sujood. You make the dua.
If it is Sallallahu Alaihi Nabi that you want to make, you make Sallallahu Alaihi Nabi.
You know that is upon your choice now that you are making dua in your sujood.
What may become an innovation is that you are doing that in the last sujood.
And every day it's the last sujood.
So that it becomes as if the last sujood is a sujood for extra dua.
Don't do it like that.
Don't particularize what the Sharia generalizes.
You can make your dua in any of the sujood.
Now don't make it become as if the only time you can make your dua a sujood is when you are upon the last sujood.
But if you want to make dua in sujood, you can make Sallallahu Alaihi Nabi.
If you want to make dua in all the eight sujood of a four raka'ah Sallah, yes you can make Sallahu Alaihi Nabi.
Don't forget that is if you are praying alone or you are leading the people in prayer.
Don't also forget if you lead the people in prayer
and you want to so prolong your Sallah making dua in the sujood.
Don't forget that the people behind you have a right to have the Sallah not so long becoming a difficult thing upon them.
So don't forget their rights.
But if you are upon your own nawafil, you are upon your own nawafil,
then say Sallahu Alaihi Nabi in every sujood, there is no blame at all.
Because Sallahu Alaihi Nabi is dua and you'll be granted your dua.
And in fact for one and each of the Sallahu Alaihi Nabi that you make,
Sallallahu Alaihi Nabi, each time you make Sallahu Alaihi Nabi,
you know all the rewards that are connected to it.
Ibn al-Qayyim mentioned about 33 things that are connected as things of virtue to your making Sallahu Alaihi Nabi.
So it's a very, very valuable thing to do.
I hope that this detailed explanation about that is clear.
You can make your Sallahu Alaihi Nabi in every sujood,
as long as you don't take it to mean the last sujood or the first sujood or the third sujood.
You can do that in your nawafil.
You can make dua after your Sallahu Alaihi Nabi.
All of these are lawful.
But the basic requirement for every sujood are those things that we said,
subhanarabiyya la'ala, or,
subburhu kuddusu rabbu l-malayikati wal-rooh.
I hope that it is clear.
How about Yousuf?
I mean, there's a question here.
If a woman becomes still after height,
must she use her hair before taking a bath,
or it suffices to just pour the water and scrub?
It suffices to pour water,
if you are making a bath after your busu.
It suffices that you just pour water on the head.
You don't have to lose your hair.
But don't forget, from the things you have to do about busu,
that water comes all over the body,
and you start with the head.
Soak your hair with water.
But in terms of now losing it,
that is encouraged,
because it will encourage and support the fact that water touches every,
every part of the hair.
The condition of losing the hair,
I think that in the hadith of Umar Salama,
many of the scholars say that it was having to do with the ghusl of hajj.
It was having to do with the ghusl of hajj.
But as for hajj, at any other time,
if you lose the hair, okay.
If you only soak your hair with water and continue with your ghusl,
it's okay to be mela.
Like the question say, must I?
No, you must not.
But if you do, inshallah, it is going to help achieve the overall aim,
that from the arkan of ghusl is that water touches all parts of the body.
I hope that it is clear.
Another question says,
Can I say, Allah o Alam,
or as a response to a question that I know and answer,
but I don't want to mention it.
A question that you know.
Yes, but I don't want to discuss it.
You don't want to discuss the matter.
Perhaps like Martin Auli Sababin,
perhaps for a particular wisdom, or a reason, or a cause.
Yes, it is true that Allah o Alam, if you ask the question,
it's an absolute truth,
that absolute knowledge belongs to Allah subhanahu wa ta'ala.
Allah knows best, in every circumstance,
in every circumstance, whatever we know,
the best of the knowledge of it belongs to Allah.
That is one of the meanings of
What occurs in the knowledge of Allah,
all of it cannot be known by Mankind.
What occurs, we need to know, regarding Allah subhanahu wa ta'ala.
We can't know everything all.
That is to say, ilmillah.
Either you translate it, you explain it to me,
what is in the knowledge of Allah,
or knowledge about Allah's essence himself.
That our knowledge cannot encompass it,
about Allah's essence, everything about it, no.
Or about the things inside his knowledge, subhanahu wa ta'ala.
Our own knowledge cannot encompass everything.
What that means is that he is ever absolutely more knowledgeable
than all of us in every circumstance, subhanahu wa ta'ala.
So, Allah is alamu in every circumstance.
This is wa anna allaha qad ahata bi kulli shay'in ilmah.
Allah subhanahu wa ta'ala, his knowledge encompasses everything,
ahata bi kulli shay'in.
As for Banu Adam, our own knowledge is small.
Very small knowledge.
When he spoke about our knowledge, he says,
wa ma hu ti tum min al ilmillah qalila.
So, we've not given you from knowledge except a little.
So, Allah is alamu in every circumstance and in every situation.
So, if you are not saying anything,
and you say Allahu alamu, yes, what you said is true.
If you explain and yet you come back and say Allahu alamu,
it's also true.
So, in any case, Allahu is alamu.
But, make sure that you are not employing that situation,
that expression to imply any sort of a deceit or the likes of that.
No, don't deceive the people using these kinds of expressions.
But, the expression is true in itself.
I hope that it is clear.
Can you hear me Sir?
I can hear you speak slowly, you have our use of...
Now we are shooting.
Okay, good.
Now, another question says,
can we say, give to Kesar what belongs to Kesar?
Okay, that is, give to Kesar what belongs to Kesar.
It has a second expression.
It's a statement common with the Christians,
and to God what belongs to God.
That's what they say,
give to Kesar what belongs to Kesar,
and to God what belongs to God.
So, meaning that in the affairs of your life,
just follow the worldly rules,
but in the affairs of your worship,
just that time you can be a servant of God.
No.
In our own Deen, Islam,
it is,
O people of Iman,
come into Islam,
completely and absolutely submitting in Islam.
So, Islam is something you come into,
completely in the affairs of your Deen.
Everything is for Allah,
in your Deen, in your religion,
in your worship, in your devotion.
Everything is for Allah,
in your worldly life.
Everything is for Allah too,
So, you can now say, are you also saying that,
when I transact business,
it should be for Allah?
Yes.
How?
The rules in your business transactions,
must be in line with the instructions of the Sharia.
Whatever Allah has prohibited,
you must not do.
...
Can we hear me, Ikhoa?
So, in the matters of your business transactions, Allah has prohibited rebar.
So, if you avoid rebar, and very many other business transactions,
that the Sharia has prohibited, by that, your worldly life regarding your business,
would be for the sake of Allah. Why?
Because you have employed the restrictions, and the limitations of the Sharia in it.
So, it becomes deen for you, it becomes worship for you.
So, when you avoid rebar, for example, in your business transaction,
that business transaction becomes an Ibadah for you, for the sake of Allah.
When you avoid selling what you don't have, for example, you don't own, for example,
that your business transaction becomes a means of Ibadah for you.
So, this is how our worldly affairs becomes Ibadah for we, the people of Islam.
When you dress, you wear clothes, what you wear, it fulfills the limit,
the instructions, the restrictions of the Sharia are considered,
when you select the material that you wear, and how you wear it.
All of these have rules in our religion, Islam.
In fact, as simple as wearing a ring, which hand do you wear the ring?
It is very common now, even men now, many men, usually now wear rings.
It's lawful for a man to wear a ring, but on which fingers will he wear them?
The Sharia prohibits us from wearing fingers on our first finger,
and the middle finger, as it's in the Hadith of Ali ibn Abi Talib in Sunnah Nabi Dawood.
And many of the scholars affirm that wearing the finger, wearing rings on that finger,
we call the ring finger. That is the finger, before the small finger,
we call it the ring finger. Men don't wear a ring on that finger.
The Ulama say it is from the Tashabu bil Kuffa, copying non-Muslims.
So three fingers we cannot wear rings on. The first finger, the middle finger,
and what they call the ring finger. That word itself, the ring finger,
itself has some connection with worship amongst the non-Muslims.
So these three fingers don't wear rings on them.
So you only have the thumb and the small finger.
The Prophet himself, when he wore a ring, he wore the ring on the small finger.
So if you wear your ring on the small finger, you are making Ibad,
you are following the Sunnah, and you do that with the intention of
following the Prophet Muhammad, alayhi salatu wassalam.
But the same thing in your dealings in politics, in your dealings in economics,
in your dealings in your social affairs, that are the laws of the Sharia, guiding everything.
So at the end of it, you see a Muslim coming into Islam completely,
and he does not have any part of his life that you can say,
let us leave religion apart. Kuffar says this a lot online and social media now.
Let's leave religion apart. No, the Muslim does not have any time or place or thing that he is
doing. He can say, leave Islam apart. No, let's leave religion apart. No.
A Christian can say that because they don't have much guidance in the details of life.
They don't have guidance. Christians, their deen is upon ignorance.
They don't have guidance in the details of life. Unfortunately, the Yehud,
they have a lot of details, just like we have in Islam.
The unfortunate thing about them is that
the Jews we mean, in their own cases, the Yehud we mean,
they have knowledge, but they abandon it. They are very sinful and wicked set of people.
They abandon guidance from Allah. So they are not far away from the Christians,
but they are worse than them because they have guidance, but they abandon it. The Christians
don't even have guidance at all. So these kinds of expressions to give to Caesar what belongs to
Caesar and to God what belongs to God. No, it's wrong for a Muslim. Everything belongs to Allah.
Did you not hear what Allah commanded the messenger to say,
Salatu was-salam, that
My Salat, my devotion in Salah, all everything I do in my life regarding
reverence for Allah, and the entirety of my existence itself as an individual,
Lillah, it's for Allah. No Caesar, no division between Caesar. No,
Caesar does not have anything. In fact, in our obedience of our leaders,
who told us to be in our leaders? Did Allah not say to us in the Quran that
that the Prophet Muhammad not give us proof whose guidance about governance
and obedience to constituted authority? In all of that as we obey our leaders,
well as we lead us, there are instructions in the Quran and the Sunnah.
There are instructions in the Quran and the Sunnah about leading itself,
about being a judge if you are a judge in the court of law. What do you judge? How do you judge?
What are rulings itself? In fiqhul Islam, there is kitab al-qabr, rulings, judgments
that you must understand to be able to gain the ability to also give judgments in similar cases,
rulings of the Sharia. So inside Islam, everything is for Allah.
Come into Islam completely. Allah also said to us, say that believe, act upon it.
All of them is Lillah, not for Allah and then for another person. No, Lillah, all of them.
And this is the basic difference between we the people of Islam and the people of Kufr.
Amongst the people of Kufr, yes, they can choose to be in devotion to Allah at any point. They don't
know guidance. When they get to the churches today, it's a Sunday now, you see everybody's
clapping, singing, dancing. Who told them to do all of that as a means of worship for Allah?
But for us, the entirety of our worship is codified, clear, properly legislated.
We call the Avan when it is time for Salatul Fajr. In fact, for Salatul Fajr, there are two Avan's.
We call the Avan. We know when we go to the masjid. When we come to the masjid,
we know what we do first. Everything is well guided. So in our own deen, there is no Siza,
there is no God separate, Siza separate. Everything is for Allah. Lillah, all of them.
So be careful when a Christian begins to tell you in any discussion, let's leave religion aside.
Tell him, I'm a Muslim. There is no time religion is ever left aside. Islam is ever left aside.
If you tell me to leave Islam aside, then you are telling me to be behind shaitan.
Because the Quran says, once you are not in Islam, that new path that you have brought
about for yourself, it is main khutwah to shaitan. And Allah warned you.
This matter is common now. Airlines, be careful. There is nothing you do or say,
except that you have been guided by Islam. It remains for you to follow the guidance
or follow your desires. And then by that, you will be being a slave to the big bits of shaitan.
May Allah protect all of us. May Allah guide all of us. I hope that this is clear about Yusuf.
What is the ruling of interpreting in sign language to a dev during khutbah?
The ruling of making the sign language to someone who is a
deaf during the khutbah of the Imam. This question has some backgrounds to it.
The first thing in the background to it is that the person interpreting the sign person
has the duty upon himself for himself to sit down in the masjid to listen to the Imam.
The person interpreting himself, he has the duty by himself
to sit down in the masjid to listen to the khutbah of the Imam. Something similar to that is
those who translate as the Imam is giving the khutbah, not a pre-translation that was replayed.
The translation, perhaps the Imam speaks Arabic and there is someone speaking Yoruba interpreting
Yoruba or the Imam is speaking Yoruba. As we have in many universities, someone is making an
translation. You can ask this same question. Is that lawful? Why? Why are you asking this question?
That I'm saying that there's a background to it. That person interpreting and translating has a
duty himself to be listening. The only person that is clearly allowed to speak during the
khutbah of the Imam is the Imam himself. Unless the Imam asks you a question, then you can answer.
If the Imam asks you a question, you can answer. If he speaks to you directly, you can answer.
We remember the hadith of God's fan. The Prophet spoke to him. Likewise, the hadith of
the Prophet spoke to him. So if it happens that the Imam speaks to you, telling you something,
then answer the Imam. Or the Imam is addressing you. You answer the Imam,
but the Imam is talking, giving the khutbah. Somebody else is also interpreting the khutbah,
whether in a clear-cut language as we speak it or through sign language upon the use of gestures.
Is this lawful? Let us look at this question at another time. Let us, we can look at this question.
It's a very, very important question. Is it lawful for someone to interpret,
whether in language or by gesture for the deaf, while the actual Imam is upon the
member delivering the khutbah? Is that lawful? Will it come under the issues of barura?
We come back to the class with the rest of the questions properly regarding this. I've
thought about it and I've never asked any of the learned persons amongst the elders,
amongst the scholars, and I have never come across something being said about it
in the text. I will come back if I look at it and come back to class. It's very important.
We see it in the Masajid on the days of Jum'a. I will address this matter subsequently about Yusuf.
But I hope that we understand the background to it. The background to it is that everybody
should be listening to the Imam. Why should somebody be talking when the Imam is talking?
And that now becomes a norm. Should that kind of a norm be accepted at the time of the khutbah
of the Imam on the day of Jum'a, when the Prophet, alayhi salat wa salam, emphasized and said,
Even my master, al-Asr, merely touching something near you,
like stones in the masjid, or removing that from your body, or telling somebody to keep quiet.
It has gone beyond the limits on the days of Jum'a. In fact, in some cases,
it says it does not have Jum'a. That what everybody must be doing on the day of Jum'a
is to listen to the someone. So is the person giving the sign language, also listening,
is also listening, is also talking, addressing people. Likewise, the person who is giving a verbal
interpretation into another language. Is this lawful?
By the name of Allah, we will come back to plants regarding this, insha'Allah.
The same thing applies to people making video coverages. It's now common now. People,
rather than sit down to listen to the Imam, they can set their cameras. That is if videoing is law.
So they can set their cameras. But stay there, turn the camera, turn it to the Jum'a,
turn it to the Imam, turn it to this. I hope we can come back to these issues with the law,
with a better explanation, and could just prove, insha'Allah.
Can a female put ring in the ring finger, or the prohibition is for both gender?
The prohibition is for males. We discussed this earlier. The women,
the woman, she was knotted. All her life is about, is about adornment. But the woman can
put the ring on all the fingers. The prohibition is regarding males, insha'Allah. I hope that it
now. What are the two fingers that a male can use to wear the ring?
We said it during that explanation, the small finger and the thumb. But what the
Prophet used himself, because the Prophet wore rings too. There was a time he took a ring.
Al-Imam al-Tirmidhi mentioned that in his Shama'il Nabi, it's an entire book about the Prophet's
personal conduct in his day-to-day life. The day-to-day personal conduct of the Prophet,
alayhi salatu was-salam. One of the things mentioned about him was that he had a ring
at a point in time. That ring was made from silver. The ring of the Prophet is not gold.
Wearing gold is haram. So the ring was made for males. Wearing gold is haram for males.
It's allowed for women if it is properly worn. But for the males, what we can wear is the silver.
So the Prophet wore, alayhi salatu was-salam, it took a silver ring at a particular time.
And that ring had a black, is it Onyx or Chalcedony? The black mineral at the middle.
That was the head of the ring. And it had Muhammad Rasulullah on it. Allah was on top.
Rasul was at the middle. Muhammad is under, below it. So you see Muhammad, you read it from below,
up, Muhammad, down most word, Rasul, above it, then Allah above it. So this was how the ring of the
Prophet was, alayhi salatu was-salam. He used to make it as a stamp for his letters. When he wrote
a letter, he placed the ring and then he stamped it. So this ring, it was with Abu Bakr and Siddiq.
I think it got lost with Uthman Ibn Affan. So the Prophet took,
salallahu alayhi was-salam, a ring, a silver ring, and he was wearing that ring on his small finger.
So men should wear the rings on the small finger. If you are following the Sunnah by wearing the
ring, you wear the ring on the small finger. But if it is just that you are just doing your own,
then you may not earn rewards for it. So wear the ring on the small finger. As for the tomb,
even though there is no prohibition about it. So if you wear a ring on the tomb as a man,
we don't have a reason to prohibit you. We don't have a proof to say, oh no, don't.
But the Sunnah is that wear the ring on your small finger. As for the first finger, the second
finger, and the ring finger, the ulama prohibit it. And there are reports regarding that from the
Sunnah too, especially for the first finger and the middle finger. The ring finger,
that's a prohibition from the scholars because they connect it to At-Tasha Buhubi Kufar,
behaving like Kufar, who choose wearing rings to be on the ring finger, because they believe that
that connects the heart from that finger. So when you put a ring on it during marriage,
the ring helps you to sustain your marriage. So we avoid that. They do it for worship. We avoid
behaving like them. So that who sees us does not think that we also have that belief they have.
So don't put rings on your first three fingers, the first finger, the middle finger,
and the ring finger. You can put your ring on the thumb, but the Sunnah is that you have your ring
on the small finger. For men, as for women, put the ring wherever you want. If you like,
put all the fingers, put ring there, right, put ring left, ten fingers, ten rings.
For a woman, there is no blame, inshallah. I hope that this is clear by Yusuf.
Amin.
There is a mosque where they are not completely facing the Qibla,
such that only the Imam has to bend in order to face the Qibla properly. Is this solid valid?
Not facing Qibla now has misconceptions. Many times when this expression is employed,
people have misconceptions about it. Not every deviation counts as not facing the Qibla. Is
this clear? Not every deviation, every slight deviation from the Qibla. You now say, no,
it's not facing the Qibla. No, not every deviation counts as not facing the Qibla.
Because the Qibla is a direction, not a point. Please let us, that's the second rule.
The first rule regarding answering this question is that not every deviation counts as
deviation in terms of the Qibla. Some does not count. It may be deviating, but it does not count.
It does not count as from the things that will invalidate Yusuf. It does not count to say you
deviated from the Qibla. You are still within the range of the Qibla. That brings us to the
second basic rule that the Qibla is a direction and not a point. The meaning is that it has a
wide range. If you are an architect or an engineering person, you understand what I mean.
The difference between facing a point and facing a direction. There is a big difference between
facing a point and facing a direction. The Qibla is a direction and not a point.
Because Allah says,
فَوَلُّ وُجُوهَكُمْ شَطْرَ الْمَزْجِدِ الْفَرَامِ
Shatra there means in the direction of Masjid al-Haram.
فَوَلُّ وُجُوهَكُمْ شَطْرَحَمِ
This shatru is direction. So and then he said in that hadith of Abu Hurairah that
So between the east and the west is the Qibla. It means the Qibla is a direction.
It is not a point. If you understand this very well, I'm sure the issue will be simple.
So it's not every change, every slight change that counts as a change of a direction.
So in that case, sometimes the imam may be slightly bent. You are not slightly bending
and you have not moved away from the Qibla. The imam has not also moved away from the Qibla.
You have not moved away from the Qibla. Why? That slight bending is within the range of acceptance.
The slight bending is within the range of acceptance. So if it is within the range of
acceptance, then you have Salah. Both the imam and the rest of the people, you have your Salah.
The Salah is valid. I hope that this is clear by Yusuf. But if it is not within
the range of acceptance, such that we can say you are not facing this direction,
you are completely away from the direction, then in that case, if they had done it deliberately,
knowingly, they knew that this is not the direction of the Qibla and yet they faced it,
they don't have Salah. The Salah is invalid.
Because one of the shurus of Salah is the Qibla. The Qibla must be faced.
And that's what we read. It occurs in the Qur'an about two or three times,
face the Qibla, face the Qibla, face the Qibla. But it's a short, it's a short two for Salah too.
But if it's that they did not know, they were trying to find the Qibla,
study, do this, and then they ended up observing the Salah, and then later found that
where they had faced for that Qibla was not the correct Qibla, then the Salah is valid.
That is now when you say for Aynama tuvalu fattam mawajhullah. I hope that it is clear by Yusuf.
And we quality be here now.
Don't forget to make dua for us.